Inventory of the R. Freeman Butts papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- GENERAL
  - Paper delivered at Mississippi Valley Historical Association on Church and State, (1949)
  - Adult Education Committee meeting at Purdue
  - Associations: John Dewey Society (1950s); AHA (1949); AASA (1950s); PES; AAAS, (1948--51) (Box 91)
  - Associations: AASA; NCSS; Ford; AAUP; Academy of Political Science, (1940s and 1950s) (Box 92)
  - Williamstown Speech to College Personnel Association
  - Correspondence and Conferences: Ford Foundation; Gould House Conference; Foreign Student Advisors; Indian; Robert K. Hall; IIE; International Fellows; Matta Akrawi; New South Wales; Japan; Kennicott Copper; Lebanon; Malaya; New Zealand; Puerto Rico (Box 93)
  - Film Strip: Citizenship Education Project
  - Correspondence: Ronald Bosier in Puerto Rico; Russian delegation; Saudi Arabia; Thailand; UNESCO; UK; Australia, (1958) (Box 94)
  - Correspondence:, 1973-1975 (Box 95)
  - Correspondence:, 1972-1974 (Box 96)
  - Correspondence:, 1971-1973 (Box 97)
  - Correspondence:, 1971-1972 (Box 98)
  - Correspondence:, 1970-1971 (Box 99)
  - Associations: National Planning Association; NSSE; NEA Committee on International Relations; NSSE Chapter on International Education, (1965-68) (Box 100)
  - Associations: PES; SSEC; NSCTE; SPE; TEPS; Society for International Development (Box 101)
  - Speeches and articles (Box 102)
    - "Foundations of Education and the New Civism" - AESA
    - "Outstanding Foundations Books of 1973" for Educational Studies
    - "Citizenship Education" for IDEA Fellows
    - "Public Education and Political Community" for AERA
    - "Citizenship Education for ECS in Miami
    - "Citizenship Education for Memphis State
    - "Public Purpose of Public Education" for Hutchins Center
    - Research Proposal for Carnegie and NIE
    - Bibliography on Comparative History of Higher Education - for Aspen Institute, (1973)
  - Speeches and articles (Box 103)
    - Bibliography on Comparative Higher Education prepared for Aspen Seminar (103 pp.), (1973)
    - Book of Readings on African Education
    - Attacks on the Public School Idea - Nation, (1973)
    - "New Futures for Comparative Education" for Comparative Education Review
    - Speech on Foundations of Education for ATEA - Kampala
    - "Invisible College" - Alumni celebration at T.C.
    - "Charting Our Course on the Way To..." New Orleans Article on Toynbee
    - Promotion material for Education of the West
  - Articles and speeches (Box 104)
    - "The Idea of the National Institute of Education" prepared for delivery in New Delhi, India, (1962)
    - ATEA Keynote Speech - Kampala, following opening remarks by Idi Amin, March 1971
    - "Invisible College" speech at TC Symposium
    - "European Models of Higher Education" for conference at Bloomington, Indiana
    - "Teacher Education and Modernization" at Williamsburg Conference on World Crisis in Education, (1966)
    - Early articles on the Veteran, (1946)
    - "Emergency Demands on Higher Education" in Schools and Society, (1942)
    - Articles on Teachers for East Africa and India
    - TC Proposal for Cross-cultural research
    - Reviews of Education of the West
    - Correspondence with McGraw-Hill and Creative Book Services
  - TC Proposals for research on international education (Box 105)
  - Mohonk Conference speech on African Higher Education
  - Civilization Building article
  - "Teaching College for the World"
  - John Dewey Lecture on American Education and International Development, (1962)
  - Entebbe Conference of Teachers for East Africa
  - TEA materials
  - Religion and the Schools - for TC Record
  - Articles and Speeches (Box 106)
    - Teachers for East Africa
      - "First Impressions", (1962)
      - Opening Session -, June 1961
    - "Education for New Nationhood" - Kabul, (1962)
    - Bogley Memorial Lecture
    - Foreign Students Colloquim
    - "Educationary" at New Paltz
    - Deans of Agriculture Curriculum Conference - Fort Collins
    - "Tension in Teacher Education" for Educational Forum
  - Articles and Speeches (Box 107)
    - "Search for Freedom" - NEA Journal 25 copies, (1960)-
    - "Pedants, Pedagogues, and Persuaders" - Bowling Green, (1960)
    - Fort Collins Conference on Higher Education
    - Debate on Aid for Parochial Schools with Father McCluskey - at AASA, (1960)
  - Article and Speeches (Box 108)
    - "Open Mind" - NBC/TV
    - "No - on Public Funds for Parochial Schools"
    - Remarks at Centenary for John Dewey
    - "Scholarship and Education in a Free Society: - Oswego, NY
    - "Free Man in a Free Society" Religious Education Association, (1959)
    - "Madison, Education and the Bill of Rights - T.C. Research, (1958)
    - Report of Committee on Historical Foundations of Education - NSCTE, (1953)
    - "Education of Teachers: "If I Had My Way" - Kansas City Conference, (1959)
    - Replies to Bowling Green Speech on "Pedants, Pedagogues, and Persuaders" - uncluding Look Magazine
    - Appraisal of Maryland's Educational Program, (1959)
  - Materials for Assumptions Underlying Australian Education (Box 109)
  - Materials and Notes on Carnegie Travel Grant to England, East Africa, South Africa, West Africa, and Malaya, (1961-62)
  - Materials and notes on travel in Afghanistan, (1962) (Box 110)
  - Folders on The College Charts Its Course (1939) Permissions, Reviews by Almach and reply by Tewksbury in Social Frontier, letter from Cowley and Wittke and several other historians and educators
  - Selection as one of "Sixty Educated Books of ", 1939
  - Proposed revision of The College Charts Its Course. Chapters; and materials for the 1920s-30s, 2 and 3 (Box 111)
  - Pamphlets by Noah Porter, J.S. Mill, Mississippi College, William Smith at College of Philadelphia, and Society for the Promotion of Theology and Collegiate Education of the West
  - Revision of The College Charts Its Course. Pasted-up sheets; Mortimer Adler, (1945) (Box 112)
  - Materials for history of higher education
  - Revision of The College Charts Its Course. Proposed chapter headings: Precincts of Freedom and Control; Precincts of the Public and the Private; Flood of Enrollment: - Ride with the Tide or Raise the Sea Walls; The Mark of an Educated Student; Religion and Higher Education; Priorities for the Humanities, Sciences, and Social Sciences (Box 113)
  - Articles and Speeches by RFB (Box 114)
    - International Higher Education: "Is the World Our Campus?"
    - International Home Economics and Human Resource Development
    - "Assignment in India" - Parts I and II, (1959)
    - Article on Peru Project - CIES
    - "A Teaching College for the World"
    - NSSE Yearbook on International Education - contained in House Committee on Education - Brademas
    - Translation into Korean and Italian
  - Articles and Speeches by RFB (Box 115)
    - "Historical Perspective on American Higher Education" - chapter for Aspen Institute Seminar
    - "New Futures for Comparative Education" - Comparative Education Review
    - "Public Purpose of Public Education" - T.C. Record
    - "Public Education: Attack as a Great Idea" - Nation (1973), T.C. Perspectives, Phi Delta Kappan
    - "International Activities of T.C. Faculty", (1966-68)
  - Articles and Speeches by RFB (Box 116)
    - Mohonk Conference on Teacher Education in Africa
    - "Perspectives on International Education" - NSSE Yearbook
    - Copies of T.C. Record with RFB articles-, 1941, 1946, 1950, 1957, 1958, 1959, 1960, 1969, 1973
    - Research Proposal on Public Education submitted to NIE, (1973)
  - T.C. Annual Reports on International Education, (1961-73) (Box 117)
  - Articles and Speeches by RFB
    - Review of Storr in Political Science Review
    - Seminar at Indiana University on Higher Education
    - Educational Studies
    - Aspen Institute Seminar in Higher Education
    - Latin American Universities and Teacher Education
  - Articles by RFB in Educational Theory; Nation's Schools; T.C. Record; Teacher Education; Italian Journal of Education; Current; etc. (Box 118)
  - Alphabetical Files "O" to "T" (Box 119)
  - T.C. Affairs: Student Council; Rugg Testimonial Dinner; Dean Russell; Rugg in Middle East
  - Alphabetical Files s) "M" to "P", (1950s-60 (Box 120)
  - Michigan State Overseas Research
  - TC Affairs: Philosophy Club; Public Relations Committee; New Lincoln School; John Norton; Caswell Resignation
  - International Teaching Service
  - NY Times Clippings on RFB: Australian Fulbright; Speech on Academic Freedom
  - Alphabetical Files "H" to "L" (Box 121)
  - Eisenhower Installation
  - Intergroup Relations
  - Clarence Linton
  - RFB Letter to NY Times for JFK in, 1960 (Box 122)
  - Materials on Religion and Education
    - Policy Questions on Religion and Education s), (1950s-60
    - Education 202C - course on Religion and Education s), (1950s-60
    - Federal Aid Bills, (1958, 1960, 1961)
    - Senator Sam Ervin's letter and speech re: American Traditions in Religion and Education
  - Materials and Speeches on Religion and Education (Box 123)
    - Religious Education Association; Baltimore; Institute for Religious Studies; Article by Father Davis re: RFB in School and Society
    - Education 202C - Class notes on Religion and Education
  - Materials on Religion and Education. RFB Speech in Queens; Bibliographies for Education 202C; Federal aid to Education; Spellman vs. Mrs. Roosevelt (Box 124)
  - Materials on Church and State. Supreme Court decisions; State court decisions; Pamphlets; More on "Choices Before Us" (Box 125)
  - The American Tradition in Religion and Education. Reviews, ads, and correspondence; Mrs. Agnes Meyer; Martha Counts; original manuscript (Box 126)
  - Church and State correspondence: John Norton (Box 127)
  - Educational Course at Wisconsin; Tennessee papers, (1949)
  - Alphabetical files "V" to "Z"
  - Caswell Inauguration: Conference on Educational Leadership for a Free World, (1955)
  - Alphabetical files "A" to "C", (1950s) (Box 128)
  - RFB Suggestions to Committee for next President of T.C.
  - Dictation discs from Landon on TEA Group C
  - Alphabetical files "C" to "F" (Box 129)
  - TC Committee on Grades; Foreign Students; Proposed Faculty Committees and Sections; New Courses
  - Correspondence - Norman Cousins
  - Council on Research in Social Science
  - Current Magazine
  - ACLU Committee on Church and State
  - Evaluation of College of Education at University of Texas, (1970) (Box 130)
  - T.C. Statutes, Revision of, 1956-57
  - RFB personal books donated to T.C. Library, (1974-75)
  - Membership lists: AESA, CIES, AHA, East-West Center
  - Membership lists: HES, PES (Box 131)
  - Formation of T.C. Statutes s), (1940s-50
  - Minutes of Teachers Guild Chapter at T.C. kept by RFB, (1942-45)
  - NSCTE Committee on Historical Foundations of Education, (1950-51)
  - NSCTE Committee on Historical Foundations of Education: History of Educaton Report (Box 132)
  - NSCTE History of Education Section
  - NSCTE History of Education Section s), (1950s-60 (Box 133)
  - Atlantic City and New York City Programs s), (1940s-50
  - NSCTE Executive Committee
  - History of Education Journal, (1950s)
  - NSCTE Executive Committee; RFB Presidency Platform; Emergency Tasks; Foundations Drafting Committee (1948-49), (1953-54) (Box 134)
  - History of Education Journal, Vol. I, No. 1
  - Alphabetical files "A" to "Z"; "A" to "G" (1966-67), (1967-68) (Box 135)
  - Alphabetical files "A" to "Z", (1968-69) (Box 136)
  - Alphabetical files "A" to "Z"; "A" to "M" (1964-65), (1965-66) (Box 137)
  - Alphabetical files "N" to "Z", (1964-65) (Box 138)
  - University of Texas Evaluation Team
  - Terre Haute Conference of Educational Organization Presidents, (1968)
  - RFB Article on Toynbee
  - Union for Experimenting Colleges
  - UNESCO Conference at Airlie House
  - International Institute for Educational Planning - Paris, (1966-67)
  - IIEP Conference, (1967, 1969) (Box 139)
  - UN International School
  - Venezuelan visitors to T.C.
  - White House Conference on International Cooperation, (1965)
  - Williamsburg Conference on World Crisis in Education, (1967)
  - Visits to Wisconsin and Wyoming
  - Planning Seminar for University of Wisconsin - Green Bay, (1967)
  - Conference and National Organizations (Box 140)
    - WCOPT - Nairobi; World University; AACTE; AASA; AESA, (1970-71)
  - Conferences and Organizations (Box 141)
    - AASA; NSCTE; AACTE; AESA
    - National Standing Conference on Foundations of Education, (1971)
  - Standing Conference of Six Societies (Box 142)
  - AESA Proceedings
  - AESA Conferences (early, 1970s) (Box 143)
  - Six Societies
  - RFB Papers, (1980s)
    - "International Human Rights"
    - "Teaching About the Constitution"
    - "Foreward" to Daring to Dream
    - "Strengthening the Humanities Connection" PTA Today
    - Liberal Education and the Revival of Civic Learning
  - Correspondence (Box 144)
- LAW-RELATED EDUCATION, 1970s
  - Coalition for Law-Related Education, 1981-1984 (Box 145)
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews, 1982
  - Governor's Advisory Committee/California State Department of Education, ECIA Chapter 2, Center for Civic Education/Law in a Free Society
  - "Teaching the History and Principles of American Political Thought," seminar presented by Law in a Free Society and National Endowment for the Humanities, 1983
  - "Strengthening the Humanities Connection," Law-Related Education Futures Conference, Aspen Institute, 1980
  - Law in a Free Society - Humanities proposals
  - Law-Related Education, Leadership Training Conference, 1981
  - Law-Related Education Program, grants and applications
  - National Conference on Civic Education, 1978
  - Law in a Free Society, Directors, 1980
  - Law in a Free Society, 1980-1981 (Box 146)
  - Law in a Free Society, 1977-1978
  - Law in a Free Society, Executive Committee
  - Council for the Advancement of Citizenship, Conf. Report, 1982
  - Jennings Randolph Forum for the Advancement of Citizenship, working draft proposal, 1981 (Box 147)
  - Jennings Randolph Forum, future plans
  - Council for the Advancement of Citizenship (C.A.C.), membership
  - C.A.C., linkages
  - C.A.C., membership lists
  - C.A.C., business meetings, 1983
  - C.A.C., Executive Committee, September 30, 1982
  - C.A.C., Board Meeting,; Executive Committee Meeting, December 9, 1981, September 15, 1981
  - Inaugural Randolph Forum, May 15-17, 1982
  - C.A.C., Randolph Forum
  - Randolph Forum, Conference Report, May, 1982 (Box 148)
  - C.A.C., brochures
  - C.A.C., June, 1981
  - Wingspread Citizenship Conference
  - C.A.C., Center for Citizenship Education, Washington, D.C., 1979-1980
  - National Task Force on Citizenship Education (Box 149)
  - National Task Force, Press conferences, New York and Washington, D.C., February 1-2, 1978
  - National Task Force, working papers and recommendations
  - National Task Force, San Francisco meeting, May, 1976
  - National Task Force, transcript, Washington, D.C. and San Francisco, February 4, 1976
  - National Task Force, "Education for Responsible Citizenship"
  - U.S. Office of Education, "Citizen Education Today," early draft, Fall, 1977
  - U.S. Office of Education, Citizen Education Task Force Report, Fall, 1977 (Box 150)
  - U.S. Office of Education, Citizen Education Task Force Report, Special Committee to Advise
  - U.S. Office of Education, Citizen Education Task Force Report, 1977-1978
  - National Conference on Citizenship and Education, Kansas City, September 21-23, 1976
  - Citizenship Education Conference, Advisory Committee Meeting Agenda, July, 1976
  - Citizen Education Report, Elizabeth Farquhar
  - "Civic, Citizenship, and Citizen Education: A National Conference Evaluation Report," U.S. Office of Education, November, 1976
  - U.S. Office of Education, Council of Chief State School Officers, National Conference, September 20-23, 1976 (Box 151)
  - Smithsonian Inst., Woodrow Wilson Intl. Center for Scholars, Federal Education Policy Project, transcript of proceedings
    - December 1976
    - February 1977
  - Recommendations (by R. Freeman Butts) for Danforth Action in Civic Education, March, 1980
  - Danforth, Mehlinger and Remy, Reconceptualization of Citizenship Education, 1979-1980
  - Danforth National Commission Exploratory Session, November, 1977
  - Danforth Trustees, Report of R. Freeman Butts, January, 1978 (Box 152)
  - Recent and Related Developments in Citizenship Education, regarding a National Commission
  - Names for Danforth
  - Danforth Foundation, travel plans, Spring, 1977
  - Danforth travel, Fall 1977
  - Danforth, general correspondence
  - Danforth Project Conferences
  - Danforth, consulation and expenses, 1977-78
  - Mosher, Ralph A., "A Curriculum in Moral Education for Adolescents," reprint and printed matter, (2 folders)
  - Citizen Action, Fred Newmann, Madison, Wisconsin
  - Project ACT (Affirming Our Cities Together), Minneapolis/St. Paul, Dian Hedin
  - Danforth Foundation, Brookline Moral Education Project, Brookline High School, Junior and Senior High School Curriculum (Box 153)
  - Center for Moral Education, Harvard University, "The Causes of the American Revolution"
  - Sullivan, Paul J. and Mary Dockstader, "Values Education and American Schools: Worlds in Collision?" Tacoma Public Schools, Ethical Quest Project Overview
  - "Law and the Humanities: A Design for Elementary Education," American Bar Association, Special Committee on Youth Education for Citizenship (Box 154)
    - Reports, minutes, November, 1976; (3 folders)
    - Symposium, May, 1978
  - Law-Related Education, team update reports, 1979
  - American Bar Association, Summer Institute, August, 1978
  - American Bar Association, Youth Education for Citizenship, Symposium on Elementary Education, May, 1978; (2 folders) (Box 155)
  - Alliance for Citizen Education
  - National Conference on Citizen Participation, Lincoln Filene Center, Washington D.C.
  - Department of Health, Education and Welfare, U.S. Office of Education, Study Group on Law-Related Education (Box 156)
  - Farnen, Dr. Russell F., Jr., "Formulating a Comprehensive Index of Political Education in Contemporary America,", May, 1977
  - Miscellaneous printed matter and booklets relating to Law-Related Education
  - Miscellaneous printed matter and booklets relating to Law-Related Education programs, including Research for Better Schools, I.P.L.E., Law in American Society, Law in a Changing Society, Mershon Center, Indiana Curriculum Center, C.R.F. and H.E.W. (Box 157)
  - Law-Related Education, American Bar Association, Law in American Society, Law in a Free Society
  - Miscellaneous printed matter and booklets relating to Law-Related Education (Box 158)
  - Indiana University, Social Studies Development Center
  - Research for Better Schools
  - Law in a Changing Society, "Evaluation of Law in a Changing Society Program: Houston/West Texas and Related Projects" (Box 159)
  - Miscellaneous printed matter and booklets relating to Law-Related Education
  - "Theory in Stages," Lawrence Kohlberg (Box 160)
  - "The Just Community School: The Theory and the Cambridge Cluster School Experiment," Kohlberg, Wasserman and Richardson
  - Dissertation on Cluster Schools, Wasserman
  - "Collected Papers on Moral Development and Moral Education," Lawrence Kohlberg, Spring 1973
  - Evaluation of Law in a Free Society Authority by Cluster School Staff (Box 161)
  - Curriculum (?), Carnegie-Mellon, Pittsburg, PA, Ted Fenton
  - Carnegie-Mellon
    - 10th Grade Social Studies, Units I-III
    - 10th Grade Social Studies, Units IV-V
    - 11th Grade Social Studies
    - 10th Grade English (Box 162)
    - 11th Grade English
  - Fenton's Staff Development Workshop
  - "Law-Related Education Materials: Evaluations and Recommendations," Tri-County Law-Related Education Project (Box 163)
  - Law-Related Leadership Seminar, Airlie, Virginia, September, 1979
  - American Bar Association, Special Committee on Youth Education for Citizenship, Subcommittee on Elementary Education, N.E.H. grant, 1977-1980
  - American Bar Association, Special Committee on Youth Education for Citizenship, Final Report, "Law and the Humanities: A Design for Elementary Education"
  - Miscellaneous printed matter and booklets relating to Law-Related Education
  - American Bar Association, Special Committee on Youth Education for Citizenship, Elementary School projects, Lake Tahoe, California, 1979 (Box 164)
  - Miscellaneous printed matter and booklets relating to Law-Related Education
  - American Bar Association, Special Committee on Youth Education for Citizenship, Norman Gross, "Law and the Humanities: A Design for Elementary Education" (Box 165)
  - Social Studies School Service, catalogs, 1978-1982
  - "Ounces of Prevention: Toward an Understanding of the Causes of Violence" Final Report to the People of California, State of California Commission on Crime Control and Violence Prevention, 1982
  - Miscellaneous printed matter and booklets relating to Law-Related Education
  - American Bar Association, Special Committee on Youth Education for Citizenship, Regional Conference on Law-Related Education (Box 166)
    - General information and bulletins
    - Agenda book
    - Framingham, Mass., April, 1976
    - Chicago, 1982
    - Washington, D.C., 1981
    - Houston, 1981
    - Indianapolis, 1980
    - Dallas, 1980
  - Conference on Education for Law, Justice and Citizenship, San Jose, March, 1977
  - American Bar Association, Special Committee on Youth Education for Citizenship. (Box 167)
    - Law-Related Education Futures and Leadership Seminar, Aspen, Colorado, October, 1980
    - Salt Lake City meeting, May, 1980
    - Advisory Commission, 1978-1980
    - General, 1976-1978 (Box 168)
    - Law-Related Education Futures Conference, "Strengthening the Humanities Connection," Aspen, Colorado, 1980
  - Miscellaneous printed matter and booklets relating to Law-Related Education
  - Law in a Free Society (Box 169)
    - Board of directors
      - 1982
      - 1983
      - 1984
    - "An Overview of the Law in a Free Society Project"
    - Workshops, Area Coordinating Committees, miscellaneous material, 1977-1979
  - 3rd Jennings Randolph Forum, May, 1984
    - Position papers and materials for discussion
    - General plans and programs
    - Early Forum committee meetings, Board of Directors
  - 2nd Jennings Randolph Forum, May, 1983 (Box 170)
    - Programs
    - Planning
    - Draft proposals
    - Conference report
    - "Civis, Civitas and Civilitas: A New Focus for the Year 2000," by Senator Jennings Randolph
  - Inaugural Jennings Randolph Forum, 1982
    - General
    - "The New Federalism," conference report
  - Council for the Advancement of Citizenship
    - Citizenship Education newsletters, 1983-1984
    - Bicentennial Commission, 1982
    - Langton - Civic participation
    - Grant proposals to Exxon et al., 1982-1983
    - Proposal to N.E.H., 1982 (Box 171)
    - N.E.H. planning grants, October 1981-June 1982
  - Citizenship Education Project (C.E.P.), Teachers College, 1946-1960
  - Westin's Center for Research and Education in American Liberties, Teacher's College, Columbia University, 1965-1971
    - General
    - "The Educational Milieu"
    - "A Proposal to Develop Citizenship Education Objectives"
- PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
  - American Educational Studies Association (A.E.S.A.) (Box 172)
    - Executive Council, 1980-1984
    - Law-Related Education, 1981
    - Reflections on the Foundations Profession: Challenges for A.E.S.A.
  - Teachers' College Press, "The New Pluralism and the New Civicism"
  - The Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions
  - University of Virginia, Charlottesville and Arlington, October, 1978
  - Cleveland Conference, 1976-1981
  - The Foundations Idea
  - Re-examination of the Original Foundations Idea, October, 1964